hey what's up guys my name is a chana
welcome back to my say plus plus series
festival haircut
second of all today I'm gonna be talking
all about libraries in C++ and
specifically how we can use external
libraries in our project so if you used
to other languages such as Java or C
sharp or Python or something like that
adding libraries is a pretty trivial
task you might be using a package
manager you might not be but either way
it's usually pretty straightforward when
it comes to C++ everyone seems to have
problems and back in the day I had
issues with this as well and I don't
even know why it's there actually really
simple and hopefully this video will
kind of help clear it up for you but
basically there are a few strategies
that we can actually take when we're
dealing with libraries in C++ and I'm
gonna kind of show you my way as well as
maybe discuss some of the other ones but
first of all I hate the idea of package
managers and I hate the idea of linking
to kind of other repositories or all
that stuff my my ideal project setup is
that if you check out my repository my
code repository from github or whatever
you should have everything you need in
that repository just straight away fee
for you to actually be able to compile
and run the application or the project
or whatever right there should be no
kind of syncing up with package managers
downloading other libraries all that
stuff I hate all of that I just want
especially with C++ there are some
package managers for other kind of
languages which makes sense I'm
specifically obviously talking about C++
this is the C++ series but for C++
I just want stuff to work I just want to
be able to clone the repository and I
want it to compile and run so for that
reason I tend to actually keep versions
of my dependencies all the libraries
that I'm using in the actual solution in
the actual project folder so I've
actually got copies of those that visit
those physical binaries or code
depending on which way I go without as
well in my actual kind of working
directory of my solution that kinda
brings me to another point
should I be compiling these myself or
should I just be linking against
pre-built binaries now for most serious
projects I would absolutely recommend
actually building the source code if
you're using Visual Studio you can just
add another project which contains your
kind of source code of your
dependency of your library and then
compiled that into either a static or
dynamic library however if you don't
have access to the source code or if
you're planning just this is a quick
project I don't want to spend time
setting this up because it's kind of a
throwaway thing or it's just a it's
nothing serious then I would probably
lean against the binaries because it's
just gonna be quicker and easier so
today specifically we're going to be
linking against binaries we're not going
to be grabbing the source code of an
actual kind of dependency of an actual
library and compiling it ourselves I
might save that for another video if
you're interested in that let me know
leave a comment below but today we're
just gonna be dealing with binaries and
specifically what we're going to be
dealing with is a library called GL FW
now my open GL series which is all about
OpenGL and graphics program you saw like
that in episode 2 which I've linked up
there as well we actually did download
gel of W and Lincoln so you can take a
look at that if you'd like maybe I show
some extras some extra things there but
today we're actually going to go through
it slowly and take a look at everything
but if you kind of want to see it in a
context of a real application then check
that series out another thing to note is
the binaries might not be available for
your actual project right for your
actual library that you want to link so
you may actually be forced to build it
yourself this is especially true with
like Mac and Linux because for UNIX
systems people usually just love
building code for Windows a lot of
people who use windows just want stuff
to work like like me I just want things
to work so that's why preview binaries
exist and again I'm just saying that in
a more kind of professional a lot of
project in in a space where I actually
had time I would for sure compile it
myself because it helps with debugging
it helps with if you want to modify the
library and change it a little bit I do
that quite frequently I just love having
it having the source code right there in
the visual studio solution but today
let's talk about binaries so ever here
we have Chillicothe org which contains
the which is the gfw website there are a
few downloads here if you click this
download button and we'll download the
source code for gfw but instead we're
going to go to download and you can see
that we have precompiled binaries for
Windows another great example here you
can see for Linux and Mac OS you have to
compile it yourself but for Windows we
have these binaries now this brings us
to our first question
do I want 32-bit binaries or 64-bit
binaries this has nothing to do with
your actual operating system if you're
running Windows 10 64 bit like I am that
doesn't mean that you should be grabbing
the 64-bit binaries what that means or
like the way that you choose the ones
you want is for your target for like for
your application target so if I'm
compiling my application as an x86
application as a win32 application then
I would want the 32-bit binaries if I'm
compiling a 64-bit application I was
64-bit binaries make sure you match them
together because if you don't they won't
link so in this case I'm going to just
be making a 32-bit application so I'm
going to grab the 32-bit Windows
binaries and download them once I've
downloaded and extracted them we'll have
this folder over here inside there we
have a bunch of folders and some other
text files and this is kind of the
typical layout like yes all the typical
organizational structure that we have
with libraries in C++ there are two
parts to a library usually includes and
libraries right so an include kind of
directory and a library directory or a
Lib directory so what the include
directory is is a bunch of header files
if you don't know how linking works in C
bottles or what I even mean by link you
check out the house if it was linking
works video that I've made in the top
right corner there it covers this stuff
in depth but basically the include
directory has a bunch of header files
that we need to use so that we can
actually use functions that are in the
pre-built binaries and then the lint
directory has those pre-built binaries
and there are usually two phases to this
right there's usually dynamic libraries
and Static libraries not all libraries
it's actually surprised not all
libraries apply both of them for you
jello W does though and you can choose
if you want to link statically or
dynamically we're going to talk a lot
about the differences between static and
dynamic linking in another video
specifically about that but I'll cover
the differences for you kind of simply
here static linking means that the
library actually gets basically put into
your executable so just it's inside your
DX a file or whatever your executable is
for your operating system whereas a
dynamic library gets actually linked at
runtime so you still do have some kind
of linkage you can choose to alert a
dynamic library kind of just on the fly
literally there's a function called load
library which you can use in the Windows
API as an example and that will load you
like your dynamic library and you can
pull function pointers out of data stalk
calling functions
away but you can also have a kind of at
the application launch it loads your DLL
file which is your dynamic link library
and what I'm going to talk too much in
depth about this but there's just that
that difference of whether or not your
library actually gets compiled into your
exe file or links into your sa file and
actually having a separate file for your
library at runtime which you need to
have alongside your Exe file or just
somewhere so the UAA file can actually
load that different stuff because of
that kind of dependency of you now need
to have a DLL file as well as your exa
file usually I like to do static linking
whenever possible static linking is also
technically faster because the compiler
or the link can actually perform kind of
link time optimisation and all that
stuff linking statically can technically
result in a faster application because
there are several optimizations that can
be applied since we actually know the
function that we're linking kind of add
add actual about link time whereas with
dynamic libraries we all know what's
gonna happen we have to leave it intact
and when the library actually gets
bloated by our application of runtime
that's one that parts kind of get
patched up so usually static linking is
the way to go but for this video I'm
going to demonstrate both of those
strategies so again we have the include
files and then we have the library files
to kind of components that we need is
set up so for our compiler in our visual
studio project we have to point it to
the header files to the include file so
that we actually know which functions we
have available to us and so that we have
those function declarations that really
there's symbol declarations because they
could also be variables I'm just using
functions as an example and then we also
have to point our linker to the library
files and I'm waving my hands around
love that that's just how I talks to
deal with it and then we also need to
tell our linker this is my library file
I want you to link this so that we
actually get the function definitions
linked correctly let's go ahead and do
that for both static and dynamic
libraries so I bought this hollow world
project here in Visual Studio it's very
basic stuff but what I'm actually going
to do is inside the solution directory
make a folder called dependencies this
is how I actually manage my dependencies
in my libraries inside dependencies I'll
make another folder called GFW and
inside there I'm going to put the files
that I actually downloaded which are the
GLW library so include and live CC 2015
you can see here that they've actually
appended kind of which compiled they
used to actually compile this this
library files form in gwgw 64 and then
basically all these versions of Visual
Studio will just pick the latest one it
doesn't really matter in me at the end
of the day they are just kind of
compiled binaries and they will work
with kind of either one but we want to
use the one that's most compatible with
our current tool chain which is BC 2015
because we're using video studio 2017 so
I'll copy that and the include into this
folder here include you can see has a
gel FLV folder and then a bunch of
paedophiles perfect and Lib has three
files for us gow3 dll is the one time
kind of dynamic link library that we
actually use if we're linking
dynamically at runtime and gow3 DLL dot
Lib is actually kind of the static
library that we use with the DLL so that
we don't have to actually ask the DLL
hey can I please have a bunch of
function pointers to all of these
functions the idea is that this Lib file
actually contains all of the locations
of the functions and symbols inside jela
w3 DLL so that we can actually link
against them at compile time so in
comparison if we didn't have this Lib
file we could still use this stuff how
we have to ask the DLL file for each
function by name and actually be like
hey I want jillyfell B in it or whatever
but this live file already kind of
contains all of those locations for us
so the linker can just link to them
immediately gelatin b3 to live which you
can see is significantly bigger than the
other ones is the static library so this
is what we linked if we don't want
compile time linking and if we do that
we don't need this DLL file to be
without Exe file at runtime okay cool so
let's actually link this stuff I'm going
to right click on my hello world project
hit properties and the first thing I'll
actually do go to C C++ general and then
in additional include directories I'm
going to specify my additional include
directory now note your configuration
and platform make sure you're editing
the right ones I obviously want this to
apply for all configurations so I'll
just hit all configurations now the
include directory is the actual
directory that goes each of this include
folder so that's it I could just copy
this directory but obviously you can see
that it's in C uses yarn documents very
specific to my computer if someone ends
up cloning this from github or something
like that they're not gonna have this
path and that code isn't going to
compile what I actually want to do is
have a path that is relative to this
actual directory so hollow world is the
directory with my solution right
everyone's going to have that if they
check out my repository because this is
my repository so inside it so starting
from this solution file which I can do
by typing in solution this is a macro
that you can use in Visual Studio if I
go under here into edit you can see that
it actually evaluates to this value
which is the solution directory if I hit
macros over here I can see all of my
macros and I can type in like solution
de as an example and you can see what it
is there's also things like project
directory which is the directory of the
project you can see that it's inside
another hello world folder but the one
that we care about it's virgin directory
so we'll start off there and then we'll
basically get that relative path which
in this case is dependencies GL FW and
include so I can just grab that and
really just copy the end of that path
starting in my solution directory folder
I'll paste it into here
hit enter and that's it I'm done what I
can now do is basically just include
files relative to this directory so this
directory contains the GL FW folder
which has a file called JAL it'll be
three dot H so guess what I can do I can
just come in here and type it include GL
f w /j love w3 dot h just like that and
that will actually work if I hit ctrl f7
to compile my code you can see that I
get no errors now because this is a
compiler specified in fluid path I can
also use angular brackets and this kind
of comes to the debate of do I use
angular brackets or do I just use quotes
Mike there's no difference because
quotes will actually check the relative
paths first and if it doesn't find
anything relative to this file so
relative to the main dot CPP file it
will actually look for the compile it'll
look through the compiler include parts
now the way that I use this is basically
if this source file is in Visual Studio
so if gow3 or H is actually in in inside
my solution somewhere maybe it's in a
different project I don't care but it's
inside this solution it's included in
the solution then I will use quotes if
it's an it's
absolutely kind of external dependency
or external library that isn't in I'm
not compiling it with Visual Studio with
this actual solution then I'll use
angular brackets to kind of indicate
that it's actually external so for this
case I will write my code like this now
I haven't actually linked against the
libraries at all so I've told the
compiler that hey there's a bunch of
functions if I go to jail w3h you'll
actually see that there's a bunch of
stuff here I have a function for example
called Jill up top you in it so let's
try calling this over here my code I'll
type in into a or something equals jail
toluene is I don't know why my curly
brackets a a black that is the worst
idea ever
I'm gonna fix that after this video
anyway you can see that if I do gel 12
unit like this it looks like
everything's fine
I can hit ctrl f7 to compile my code you
can see I don't get any compiler errors
but of course if I try and actually
build my project and run it all just hit
build it's not gonna link correctly and
you'll get an error that says unresolved
external simple Jill it'll be eaten it
this is the cause of so many problems
for people what this means is that you
haven't linked your actual library the
linker can't find this jello double unit
function if we actually go to the header
file again and we take a look it's just
got a semicolon here this doesn't tell
us what the function actually does it
just tells us that the function exists
what we need to do is actually find a
definition for that function
now we could provide one I'll just show
you I'm showing you this so that you
know how it works so we know that U of W
in here takes no parameters and returns
an integer I could literally write
chillip double unit here and it's like
returns zero or something like that and
then now if I build this and compile it
you can see that it is going to
successfully generate my hello world exe
file and the build will succeed because
I'm actually providing a definition for
this function now obviously we don't
want this definition we want the one
that's actually in the library so we
need to link against the library
hopefully that clears things up so I'll
right click on holo world hit properties
to make sure again I'm in all
configurations and on the right platform
go to linker and in general now inside
link input is where I actually want to
include that chillip w3 don't live file
right I actually want to include it over
here however I don't want to have to
specify the entire path so again I could
do like you know solution directory
slash blah blah I just want to keep this
clean and just have
we don't live here so if I want to do
that I actually need to go back to
general and set my additional library
directory just like I did in C++ general
with my additional include directory so
this should be the root directory which
contains my shell w3 don't live library
file so I cannot go over here into my
Java folder go back here to live and
then this is the directory I care about
so I'm going to grab this and copy it
and then I'm going to come back to the
library directories type in solution and
then paste in that path just like that
okay so I've specified a library
directory and then I've also specify the
name of a library file that is relative
to that library directory so if I hit OK
and I try and build this now you can see
that this works fine and we don't
actually get any errors and if I was to
for example run this let's just print
the result of this to the console here 5
you can see that we actually get one
printing here which basically means that
you'll have W initialized successfully
so everything is working fine now
similarly to how I showed you how I
actually manually added a G lfwe th
function definition the same kind of
applies for a header file right if I get
rid of this include or I don't have my
header files I just don't know that
there's a function called G let's all be
eating it actually available if I try
and compile this code it's not it's not
that it's not gonna link it's just not
gonna compile because there is no such
function the compiler can't see a
function called shelf double-unit
however if I provide the actual
declaration here by typing in G left
I'll be eating it and just returning
nothing like that and hit f5 to run my
code the idea of this will actually work
however in this specific case we get an
error because G of W is actually a C
library and what we're doing here is
mangling the name with C++ I'll have a
video is specifically about kind of
using C with C + + + name mangling and
actually what's going on here but to cut
this short we need to actually add
extern C to this function declaration
which basically just says that preserve
this name as it is because you'll be
linking against a library that was built
in C so now if we compile this code you
can see that it works successfully and
if I run it as well we still get one
same result that we got when we had the
header file so just remember those
header files are kind of just best that
you
have to do this stuff yourself it's not
like the library linking is magically
includes the magic or anything like that
it's just all components of a system to
kind of go together
so the header files kind of just tell us
which functions we have available by
providing us with declarations and then
that library file provides us with
definitions so that we actually can link
to those functions and execute the
appropriate code when we call the
functions in our C++ code
okay I'm gonna wrap up the video there I
know we did talk about dynamic libraries
but this video is just been trailing I
actually thought this would be pretty
trivial to explain and it would take
like five minutes but as always I've
just gone pretty in-depth and just
talked about this a lot which i think is
a good thing we're gonna talk about
dynamic libraries in another video
though and specifically with that I'll
show you how to also kind of pull them
out if you don't have a static library
to go along with them like we do with
yellow to view some otherwise I'll show
you how to pull out functions and do all
that kind of actual runtime linking as
well as linking against an actual DL but
at compile time as well because there's
a few kind of caveats with that as well
I hope you guys enjoy this video if you
did you can have that like button you
can also help support the series on
patreon we're going to
patreon.com/scishow know you'll get
episodes earlier there are some pretty
cool new perks as well which you should
check out I will see you guys next time
goodbye
[Music]